<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new and large discourse of the trauels of sir Anthony Sherley Knight, by sea, and ouer land, to the Persian Empire Wherein are related many straunge and wonderfull accidents: and also, the description and conditions of those countries and people he passed by: with his returne into Christendome. Written by William Parry gentleman, who accompanied Sir Anthony in his trauells.</title>
            <author>Parry, William, fl. 1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101167</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836989</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836989</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 969:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new and large discourse of the trauels of sir Anthony Sherley Knight, by sea, and ouer land, to the Persian Empire Wherein are related many straunge and wonderfull accidents: and also, the description and conditions of those countries and people he passed by: with his returne into Christendome. Written by William Parry gentleman, who accompanied Sir Anthony in his trauells.</title>
                  <author>Parry, William, fl. 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Valentine Simmes for Felix Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First leaf blank except for signature mark.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Sir Anthony Sherlies trauelles.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherley, Anthony, --  Sir, 1565-1635? --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Iran --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:3"/>
            <p>A new and large diſcourſe <hi>of the Trauels of ſir Anthony</hi> Sherley Knight, by Sea, and ouer Land, to the Perſian Empire.</p>
            <p>Wherein are related many ſtraunge and wonderfull accidents: and alſo, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription and conditions of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and People he paſſed by: with his returne into Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by William Parry Gentleman, who accompanied Sir Anthony in his Trauells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by Valentine Simmes for Felix Norton. 1601.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:4"/>
            <head>A new and large Diſcourſe, of the <hi>Trauelles of Sir Anthonie Sherley</hi> Knight, by Sea, and ouer Land, to the Perſian Empire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath béene, and yet is, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbiall ſpéech amongſt vs, that
<hi>Trauellers may lie by authority;</hi> Now, whether this Prouerbe hath had authoritie, from that authority, which ſome Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers haue vſurped (neuer by iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice granted) to lie; or whether their report (albeit moſt true) yet excéeding the beliefe of thoſe auditors that wil beléeue nothing that falles not within their owne ocular experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or probabilitie of truth, ſquared by the ſame: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (I ſay) from one, or both of theſe grounds, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb hath ſprung, I am vncertaine: but certaine I am, diuerſe there are (entiteling themſelues Trauellers, for croſſing the narrow ſeas, to the neighbour partes of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardie peraduenture, or the lowe countries perhappes) from thence take authoritie to vtter lies in England (at their returne) by retaile, which they haue coyned there in groſſe. And as ſure I am, that many honeſt and true Trauellers, for ſpeaking the truth, of their owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (for in the world are many incomprehenſible mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177255:5"/>of Nature) yet becauſe it excéeds the beliefe of the vnexperienced, &amp; home-bred vulgars, they are, by them, concluded liers for their labour. How could a man, from his birth confined in a dungeon or lightleſſe Caue, be brought to conceiue, or beléeue the glorie and great mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of the viſible, celeſtiall, and terreſtriall globes, with the wonderfull workes of the great Author of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the ſame? Nay, were ſuch a one ſodainely tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the toppe of ſome mountaine or lofty Turret in a ſommers day, from whence he might beholde the glory of the heauens, repleniſhed with that moſt admirable Creſſet, who for his glittring and diuine glory, prouokes many nations of the world to performe diuine adoration therevnto. To ſée (I ſay) thoſe reſplendant and criſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line heauens ouer-cannoping the earth, inueſted moſt ſumptuouſly in height of Natures pride with her richeſt liuery; the particularities whereof, were they deſcribed according to the trueth of their nature, it might bréede a ſcruple in the naturall man, whether Man were (for tranſgreſſion) euer vnimparadized or no. And ſuch a man, of whome I ſpeake, woulde (like a ſoule ſodainely tranſferred, by the handes of Angells, from earth to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) be beheauened with the ioy he would conceiue, by reaſon of ſo glorious a proſpect, and ſuch ſoule-rauiſhing and ſenſe-bewitching obiectes. The application héereof is apparant: for were men méerely home-bred (and in that reſpect but as the man confined to his Caue) abroad in the eminent and oppulent places of the world, as alſo in the moſt remote and obſcure corners of the ſame, and there with inſearching and well diſcerning eies, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the rarieties (ſurmounting admiration) therein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, he would (no doubt) be rapt vp with ceaſeleſſe wonderment, or wondrous amazement at the ſight and conſideration of them. For mine owne part, I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to make a true relation of what mine eies ſaw, not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177255:5"/>reſpecting the iudgement of the vulgars, but contenting my ſelfe with the conſcience of the truth; beſides which, (I proteſt) I purpoſe to write nothing. This by way of preamble: now to the matter.</p>
            <p>Therefore, firſt landing at <hi>Vliſhing,</hi> we were honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably receiued and entertained, of ſir <hi>Robert Sidney,</hi> lord Gouernour of that garriſon: from whence we went on foote to
<hi>Middleborough,</hi> where we tooke a ſmall hoy that caried vs that night to
<hi>Sierichzee.</hi> From whence we then tooke our iourney to <hi>Somerdicke:</hi> From whence wee likewiſe croſſt the water the next morning, and at night we lay at <hi>Brill.</hi> Hitherto we paſſed on foote, hiering poore ſouldiers to carry our baggage, by reaſon that the froſt was ſo great, that horſes were not able to paſſe, and the way vnuſuall. From the
<hi>Brill</hi> the next day we croſſt the water; and landing, we had waggons that conueyed vs and ours to the <hi>Hage:</hi> where, no ſooner being alighted, but that ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> (attended by vs) went to viſite his Excellency, conſociated with maſter <hi>Gilpin</hi> the Quéens Agent thither, where continuing not paſt an houre to complement with the Prince, he withdrew himſelfe to his lodging to repoſe himſelfe: whither (not long after) his Excellencie and the States ſent fiftie great flaggons of wine, togither with his Paſſe through his Countrey, whereby he was to take conuoy as he thought requiſite. The next day to <hi>Leiden,</hi> ſo to <hi>Vtricke,</hi> to <hi>Dewborough,</hi> and then to <hi>Collen,</hi> the paſſage wherevnto was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous; by occaſion wherof we had ſir <hi>Nicholas Parkers</hi> troupe of horſe to conuoy vs thither; our compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hauing <hi>25.</hi> of his horſes to ride on, &amp; <hi>25.</hi> more of his troup, beſides the cornetbearer to accompany vs to
<hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> which we did in <hi>6.</hi> daies, ſpending one night merily.</p>
            <p>The next morning, ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> giuing the troupe that were his conuoy a bountifull rewarde, ſent them
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177255:6"/>backe againe; wée taking our iourney forewardes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe thoſe partes of
<hi>Germanie,</hi> as <hi>Frankeford, Norem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bege,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Auguſta,</hi> altogether by coach. From whence wee hired horſes to paſſe the <hi>Alpes,</hi> in reſpect that it was not paſſable by coach. And from thence we were tenne dayes paſſing to <hi>Venice,</hi> whither we went, with reſolution to aide the duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> in his warres againſt the Pope; who (good duke) fearing the Popes curſe, gaue ouer the warres, as the Pope would: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we remained in <hi>Venice</hi> tenne wéekes. In which time, ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> went to the Duke thereof, who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him with all princely complement, ſending him to his lodging, a roy all banquet of all kinde of confected ſwéete meates, and wine in great aboundaunce; which continued a long time. Who likewiſe commaunded that we ſhould haue libertie to ſée any thing in the cittie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the ſight, which accordingly we ſaw, to ſir
<hi>Anthonies</hi> no ſmall coſt; for in his rewards, he was there, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, moſt royall.</p>
            <p>To write of the faſhions and diſpoſitions of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> were a matter not woorth my paines, becauſe it is ſo well knowne to all men, that knowes, or haue read, or heard any thing: therefore I will goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with our iourney, and write of matter more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous, and leſſe knowne to my home-bred countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for whoſe ſake (chiefly) I haue compiled this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>In Maie next folowing our departure from England, we ſet forwards from <hi>Venice,</hi> in an Italian ſhip, which we had compounded with, amongſt others, to conuey vs to <hi>Aleppo;</hi> but by occaſion of ſome iarres wée hadde with ſome Italians (paſſengers as wée were) in the ſhip, they landed vs in an Iland of the <hi>Venetians</hi> called
<hi>Zanc,</hi> vnto which place wée were two and twenty dayes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: the captaine aſſuring vs, that we ſhoulde haue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177255:6"/>paſſed it in tenne dayes, which made vs prouide but for aftéene dayes vittaile; thoſe fiftéene dayes being expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, our vittaile quite ſpent, and hauing ſeauen dayes trauell further in that ſhip, we could for money, nor by no meanes get any vittailes of thoſe vnkinde Italians, whereby we had bin very gréeuouſly diſtreſſed, but that certaine Perſians (though Pagans by profeſſion) being in the ſhip well vittailed, and ſéeing the impious and dogged diſpoſition of thoſe Italians, ſupplied all our wants for that ſeauen dayes <hi>gratis.</hi> In which time, an Italian in that ſhippe, vſing ſome villainous and oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious ſpeaches towardes our Queenes Maieſtie, and the ſame not heard of by ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> nor any of his company in two dayes after, but then made knowne by an Italian that attended maiſter <hi>Robert Sherly:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of when ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> heard, he forthwith cauſed one of our company ſo to heate him with a billet, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible he ſhould euer recouer it. In the performaunce whereof, he made a great outcry, wherevpon all the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talians were vp in armes, being in number ſome thrée ſcore perſons, and we but foure and twenty. Howbeit, we were (with weapons drawne) preſt to defend and offend. The captaine of the ſhip thereupon demanded of ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> how any man durſt intermeddle, in that kinde, vnder his commaund? Wherevnto ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> replied, that it was an iniurie, tending to the reproach and indignitie of his Soueraigne, which hee neither would nor could indure; and therewithall told him, if he would ſubborne or abet him therein, the one ſide ſhould welter in their blood. And our ſide being rather deſirous to proſecute this point with ſwordes, then with wordes. Sir
<hi>Anthonies</hi> brother gaue the captaine a ſound boxe, which was very hardely digeſted, and much miſchiefe had like to haue fallen thereon; but by meanes of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Merchants in the ſhip, more feareful of their goods
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177255:7"/>then of the loſſe of their bloods (and yet fearefull enough of either) pacified (with much adoe) both parties, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit either part liued watching and warding vntill they put vs on ſhore, on the ſaid Iland of <hi>Zant:</hi> where they left vs hopeleſſe (God wot) of going forwards or backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. There we continued ten dayes, in which time we hired a Gréekiſh ſhip, being an open boate, and very olde, and full of dangerous leakes; yea ſo dangerous were the leakes, that in eleuen daies (in which time wée paſſed from
<hi>Zant</hi> to <hi>Candia</hi>) continually during all that time foure men had as much toile as poſſibly they could indure, to laue water out of this rotten boate: which was ſo weake, that if euen then wee hadde hadde but euer ſo little rough weather, there had all our hopes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with our carcaſſes, periſhed, and we neuer haue arriued at <hi>Candia.</hi> Where we made our abode ſome twelue dayes, vntill our boate was repaired, and made fitter to brooke the ſeas. In which time, the Gouernor of that Ile (being a Duke vnder the Venetians) ſent for ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> to his Pallace to dinner, who alſo ſent to his lodging, a very great and coſtly banquet, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe permitted vs (in great fauour) to paſſe round about the towne, to ſée the ſtrength thereof; which was reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable well fortified with ordonance and other adiuncts of warre, eſpecially on that ſide that lay towards the ſea: the other partes not ſo ſtrong, for the ditch about the Towne was drie. The Inhabitants of that towne and Iſle are (for the moſt part) Gréekes, whoſe maners and behauiors doe verifie our Engliſh prouerb, which term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any man, pleaſantly diſpoſed (by reaſon of wine, or otherwiſe) a merry Gréeke; alluding to theſe Gréekes, that alwayes ſit drinking and playing the good fellowes before their doores: ſome dauncing arme in arme vp and downe the towne: Some others making ſome other ſports, to procure laughter; and thus gameſomely doe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177255:7"/>they paſſe their time, as if they were created but for the matter of pleaſure: So that to me it ſéemed no litle won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that that Nation, which heretofore made all the world admire their wiſedome and learning, who (in regarde of themſelues) held all the worlde beſides, but Barbarians or harbarous, ſhould now become ſuch cup ſhot companions, tripping their nimble wittes with quicke and ſubtile wine, thereby turning all their déepe pollicie, into déepe carowſing, and ſhallow iocunditie. But, <hi>Tempora mutantur, &amp; nos mutamur in illis.</hi> Hauing ſpent thoſe twelue dayes, as aforeſaide, in
<hi>Candia,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe merry Gréekes, we eftſoones imbarked our ſelues for
<hi>Ciprus,</hi> to which we were ſome nine dayes paſſing: where (as the ſaying is) the Italians (with whome we paſſed to <hi>Zant</hi>) did our errand (like knights errand) againſt our comming. They made reporte to the Turkes inhabiting the ſame Ile, that we were all pirats, and that they ſhould do wel to lay hands on vs, &amp; to carry vs to the great Turk their emperor, becauſe, beſides that, we were pirats, &amp; came into <hi>Turky,</hi> but as ſpies. Wherevpon the Turkes laid handes vpon vs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon our firſt arriuall, threatning to haue brought vs to <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> howbeit they ſtaird vs in <hi>Ciprus</hi> two daies; in which time, they were indifferently well qualified, in hope of mony we promiſed them, and which they had, to their full contentment, ere we parted from them.</p>
            <p>This was the worſt welcome which we receiued on ſhoare ſince our departure from the Engliſh ſhore, and made vs moſt to doubt our ſafety. But within two dayes paſſage of
<hi>Candia,</hi> as we came towardes <hi>Ciprus</hi> (which I had almoſt omitted) there is alſo a Gréekiſh Iſle (whoſe name (I am aſhamed therfore) I haue quite forgotten) wherevpon we touched and watered, which is ſome half mile ouer, hauing one religious houſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177255:8"/>and alone, with about ſome twenty Gréeke friggets inhabiting the ſame, which is (as wée thought) an other <hi>Eden;</hi> and the moſt pleaſant place that euer our eies behelde, for the exerciſe of a ſolitary and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue life: for it is furniſhed with the foizen of all Gods good bleſſings. All kinde of fruites (as apples, peares, plumbes, orenges, lemmonds, pomegranates, and the like) in great aboundaunce groweth there: with moſt pleaſant gardens, repleniſhed with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of odoriferous floures, and wholeſome hearbes for ſallets, or medicines: wherein breaketh foorth many freſh and criſtall cléere Springs of water: hauing therewithall, cattell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as beeues and muttons there na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally bred) more than ſufficient to ſerue that houſe. In our trauelles many times, falling into daungers, and vnpleaſant places, this onely Iſland would be the place where we woulde wiſh our ſelues to end our liues. They haue alſo this helpe, that if they did want aught, ſhipping continually paſſing by that way, would ſoone ſupply it.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Ciprus</hi> (as from a place we had ſmall reaſon to take pleaſure in, our entertainement was ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſaunt) wee hired a very ſmall boate of ſome ten tunne (there being none other to hire) to tranſporte vs vnto the Holy Land, the which was but foure and twenty houres ſailing. But the Turkes (our Taxers) tolde vs, that there lay Gallies fraught with Théeues that robbed all that paſſed that way: notwithſtanding, we hoiſed vp ſaile, and put our ſelues to Sea thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, abandoning our ſelues to all the rouing aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Fortune, being accompanied with an other boate which helde her direct courſe whither we were bound, which was taken (as afterward appéered) and her men drowned. But, as God woulde haue it, (to whome, as well for that, as all our other many many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177255:8"/>preſeruations, beyond all probabilitie and expectation, we were infinitely bound) our boate, by the way, being taken by an indirect winde, to that our direct courſe, we thereby fell downe vpon <hi>Tripoly.</hi> Who being guided by an omnipotent and neuer-failing Pilote, we paſſed out of the ſea into that famous riuer <hi>Orontes;</hi> along the which we held our courſe vp into the countrie, the Iani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries or ſouldiers thereof flocking about vs, threatning, that if they might not haue what they demaunded, they would cul out ſuch of our company as beſt pleaſed them to ſerue their zodomiticall appetites, and moſt vile and villainous purpoſes.</p>
            <p>This while we ſent to <hi>Antioch,</hi> not thrée dayes iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney off, for certaine Ianizaries, to ſafeconduct vs thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which Ianizaries were of our Interpreters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, who being come, the other left vs immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, and ſo we paſſed to <hi>Antioch,</hi> conducted by the Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries which we ſent for thither, where we remained ſixe or ſeauen dayes, for the company of certaine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants that were bound to <hi>Aleppo,</hi> béeing ſix dayes ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from <hi>Antioch,</hi> betwéene which Cities, in the way, were from time to time, diuers robberies committed by ſome two hundred Arabs, vntill that inſtant that wee were at <hi>Antioch,</hi> where we heard, that the Ianizaries of <hi>Aleppo</hi> iſſued out againſt theſe robbers, part of whom they killed, and the reſt put to flight, by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, our paſſage was cléered to <hi>Aleppo,</hi> whither we were bound, and where we were right well entertained, by the Engliſh Conſulles, and the reſt of the Engliſh mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants. There we remayned about ſome ſixe wéekes at the Engliſh houſes, and feaſted (for the moſt parte) while wée there continued. And being examined by the
<hi>Baſhaw</hi> of that place, touching our intendement, ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> aunſwered, that wee were Merchants, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to trade to the vtmoſt confines of his countries;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177255:9"/>which was graunted by the <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> with his Paſſe, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Engliſh Conſulls and vice-conſulls.</p>
            <p>Leauing héere awhile to proſecute our iorney, I will ſpeake ſomewhat of the faſhion and diſpoſition of the people and country; whoſe behauiours in point of ciuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (beſides that they are damned Infidells, and Zodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miticall Mahomets) doe anſwer the hate we chriſtians doe iuſtly holde them in. For they are beyond all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a moſt inſolent ſuperbous and inſulting people, euer more preſt to offer outrage to any chriſtian, if he be not well guarded with a Ianizarie, or Ianizaries. They ſit at their meat (which is ſerued to them vpon the ground) as Tailers ſit vpon their ſtalls, croſſe-legd: for the moſt part, paſſing the day in banqueting and carowſing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they ſurfet, drinking a certaine liquor which they do call <hi>Coffe,</hi> which is made of a ſéde much like muſtard ſéede, which wil ſoone intoxicate the braine, like our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theglin. They will not permitte any chriſtian to come within their churches, for they holde their profane and irreligious Sanctuaries defiled thereby. They haue no vſe of Belles, but ſome prieſt thrée times in the day, mounts the toppe of their church, and there, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted voyce cries out, and inuocates Mahomet to come in poſt, for they haue long expected his ſecond comming. And if within this ſixe yéeres (as they ſay) he come not (being the vtmoſt time of his appoyntment and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made in that behalfe) they haue no hope of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. But they feare (according to a prophecie they haue) the Chriſtians at the end therof ſhal ſubdue them all, and conuert them to chriſtianitie. They haue wiues in number according to their wealth, two, thrée, foure, or vpwards, according as they are in abilitie turniſhed to maintaine them. Their women are (for the moſt part) very faire, barbed euery where; and death it is for anie chriſtian carnally to know them; which, were they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177255:9"/>to doe, hardly could they attaine it, becauſe they are cloſely chambred vp, vnleſſe it be at ſuch time as they go to their <hi>Baſtoues,</hi> or to the Graues, to bewaile their dead (as their maner is) which once a wéeke vſually they doo, and then ſhall no part of them be diſcouered neither, but onely their eies, except it be by a great chaunce. The country aboundeth with great ſtore of all kinds of fruit, whereupon (for the moſt parte) they liue, their chéefeſt meate being Rice. Their fleſh is Mutton and Hennes; which Muttons haue huge broade fatte tailes. This meate moſt commonly they haue but once in the day, all the reſt, they eate fruite as aforeſaide. They eate very little béefe, vnleſſe it be the pooreſt ſort. Camels for their carriage they haue in great abundance; but when both them and their horſes are paſt the beſt, and vnfit for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the pooreſt of their people eate them.</p>
            <p>They haue one thing moſt vſual among them, which though it be right wel knowne to all of our Nation that knowe <hi>Turkie,</hi> yet it excéedeth the credite of our home-bred countriemen, for relating whereof (perhappes) I may be held a liar, hauing authoritie ſo to doe (as they ſay and thinke) becauſe I am a traueller. But the truth thereof (being knowne to al our Engliſhmen that trade or trauel into thoſe partes) is a warrant omniſufficient for the report, how repugnant ſoeuer it be to the beléefe of our Engliſh multitude.</p>
            <p>And this it is, when they deſire to heare news, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence out of any remote parts of their country with all celeritie (as we ſay, vppon the wings of the winde) they haue pigeons that are ſo taught and brought to the hand, that they will flie with Letters (faſtened with a ſtring about their bodies vnder their wings) containing all the intelligence of occurrents, or what elſe is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from thoſe partes: from whence, if they ſhoulde ſend by camells (for ſo otherwiſe they muſt) they ſhould
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177255:10"/>not heare in a quarter of a yéere, for ſo long would they be in continuall trauel. As for example; when any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize are to come out of the eaſt
<hi>Indies,</hi> to <hi>Mecha,</hi> or elſe-where of like diſtaunce, pigeons are carried from
<hi>Mecha</hi> or <hi>Aleppo</hi> before hand, which is a quarter of a yéeres paſſage, then they tie (as before is mentioned) the ſaid letters about the pigeons, acquainting therby their factors what commodities they haue, and what are like to prooue moſt vendible: by meanes whereof (whiles their camels are thrée noneths in comming) they know what merchandize is fit to be kept, and what to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>Now to returne where I left, and ſo to goe forward with our iourney: wée paſſed from <hi>Aleppo</hi> through the heart of the Turkes country, the ſtrength whereof is very ſmall, whereof the chriſtian Princes are ignorant, (as it ſéems) for if they knew it, as we do, that with al cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumſpection obſerued it; doubtleſſe, they would with no great difficultie vtterly ſuppreſſe him, or ſo extreamely diſtreſſe him, that they would conſtrain him to embrace the chriſtian faith, and reſt at their deuotion, or at leaſt remoue his ſeate from the holy land, and parts adiacent. And to giue the Reader a taſte how probable this is, (leſt I ſhould be held, as one that knoweth not whereof he doth affirme) there is (as it is there commonly repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and as commonly knowne) in all <hi>Paleſtine</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> but one thouſand and fiue hundred Ianizaries that guardes thoſe citties of
<hi>Aleppo, Damaſcus, Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> As for <hi>Grand-cagro,</hi> they are not able to ſtir for diuerſe Arabs that lie in the hilles betwixt <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and it: betwéene whome and thoſe Turkes of <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cagro</hi> there is deadly feud, as the Scot ſpeaketh. As for <hi>Babilon</hi> and <hi>Balſera,</hi> they haue likewiſe continuall wars with thoſe Arabs of <hi>Arabia Felix.</hi> Beſides, there are a great number of chriſtians borne &amp; bred in thoſe partes,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177255:10"/>which would moſt willingly be aſſiſting for their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Aleppo</hi> we ſet forwards in the middeſt of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, accompanied with our Engliſh merchants thrée day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uit wit, vntil we came to a Towne called
<hi>Beerah,</hi> or <hi>Birrah</hi> by which runnes the moſt famous riuer of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> parting <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> and <hi>Syria;</hi> where wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted ſixe or ſeauen dayes, whileſt boates were preparing for vs, and other Turkiſh merchants: that beeing done, we parted from our merchants, and betooke our ſelues to the ſaide riuer of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> on the which we were ſomo thrée and twenty dayes paſſing downe the ſame. In which time we came by a caſtle called <hi>Racca,</hi> where we were to take in freſh meate, and men to rowe. But loe, there it happened, that a Turke being in one of the boats in our company, diſcharged his péece towards the ſhoare at randon, where he moſt vnhappily ſlew a Turk of the towne, (the bullet entring his braine:) by reaſon whereof, our boate, aſwell as the reſt, was ſtayed, and we conſtrained to make ſatiſfaction for the mans death: which coſt ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> for his company ſome hundred crownes. Which being payed, and wée diſcharged, we held on our courſe from thence ſome two or thrée dayes paſſage, where we were eftſoones ſtayed by the King of the <hi>Arrabs</hi> there liuing vpon the riuers ſide in Tents: before whome we were brought, whoſe handes we kiſſ: and demaunding what we were, and what buſineſſe we had in thoſe partes, we replied, we were Engliſhmen, and Merchants by our trades, comming for traffike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe partes of the world. Wherevpon this good king tolde vs that he muſt néedes ſée our merchandize, which we (God wot) durſt not contradict: and ſo he borrowed (without a priuy Seale, or bill of his hand) ſome thirtie yardes of cloth of ſiluer, vntill our returne. That being done, we had licence to departe to our boate. In whoſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177255:11"/>campe we ſawe nothing but a multitude of cammelles, mules, aſſes, horſes, ſhéepe, and goats: from whence wee paſſed to another towne called
<hi>Anna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thence, to a towne called <hi>Dire,</hi> by which there is a lake or poole of very pitch, which in their language they call, the mouth of Hell. It ſwelles in the middeſt thereof to the bigneſſe of an hogſhead, and ſo breaketh with a great puffe, falling flat, and thus continually it worketh: whereof there is no bottome to be found, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it often hath beene tried by all meanes. There was nothing elſe woorth the noting, vntill we came where we were to paſſe by land agayne. So we ſent for cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels and horſes to <hi>Babilon</hi> (being two daies iorny from vs) to carry vs thither. Where being no ſooner come, for our welcome, we had all our merchandize arreſted, for the vſe of the Baſhaw of that place, to be payed therefore, at his price and pleaſure: howbeit we had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to prouide our ſelues an houſe, and hée dealt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with vs then wée expected; for hée gaue vs, by eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, halfe the woorth of our goodes, which was good pay, from ſo ill a debter. Yet hée extorted from ſir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> a great deal of plate made of pure emerald, which hée purpoſed to beſtow on the Perſian king, by vs cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Sophy.</hi> Howbeit we preuented him, for the one halfe of our goodes, which was carried into the towne in another Turkes name that came with vs, for which fauour, we gaue him (by agréement) fortie crownes. At <hi>Babilon</hi> (being thus entertained) wée remained a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or more, in which time a Dutchman, being one of our company, had like to haue preferred vs all to the headſ-mans handling. For, being one day drunke (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his woont) and withall, bearing a grudge to ſome of our company) went in that moode to ſome of the chiefe Officers of the Turkes in
<hi>Babilon,</hi> made ſignes to them that he had ſome matter of importaunce
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177255:11"/>to deliuer to the <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> touching ſir <hi>Anthony.</hi> Which Officers ſent for an Armenian a chriſtian, that was then in towne, who had vſed ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> excéeding wel, and was beloued no leſſe of theſe Officers, to whome they ſhewed the ſignes this Dutchman had made. Hée foorthwith aunſwered, that he was a druncken compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and that ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> hadde often beaten him for his immoderate bowzing, and continuall drunkenneſſe, which was (as hée ſaide in our excuſe) the onely cauſe he thus plaied his parte. And withall, deſired them to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their Ianizaries to beate him well, and to ſend him ſo beaten to his maiſter. Which was done (by theyr commaunde) accordingly. Wherevpon ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> was conſtraind to chamber him vp cloſe, vntil we were paſt daunger: leauing money with him to carry him backe to
<hi>Aleppo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During the time we ſtaied in <hi>Babilon,</hi> we hadde all kinde of fowle, fleſh, and fiſh, with great ſtore of veniſon very cheape.</p>
            <p>The olde tower of <hi>Babel</hi> is thrée dayes iourney from this place, which by common and iuſt reporte of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Cittie, is about the height of <hi>Paules,</hi> at this time, as they by towers of the like height, in our eſtimation deſcribed it. It is not hollow, but ſollide tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout; the baſe, or foote whereof, is about a quarter of a mile in compaſſe. It conſiſtes of Brickes baked in the Sunne, of great breadth and thickeneſſe, interlined with canes pleated like mattes, which remayne much leſſe periſhed then the Brickes.</p>
            <p>The tower which is called <hi>Nabuchadnezers</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, ſtands hard by new <hi>Babilon,</hi> which is faſhioned much like the other (as it is ſaid) but not ſo high as that we ſawe, by which doth runne the famous riuer <hi>Tigris,</hi> taking his courſe through the Citie, and ſo along by this tower.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:177255:12"/> Thus, hauing ſpent a moneth, and ſomewhat more, in new Babilon, in great feare and perplexitie, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the druncken Dutchmans ſignes and tokens (as before is mentioned) ſtaying the moſt of that time for a Carauan of the Perſians, and a great company of Merchants, wée receiued Letters from Aleppo, by which wée were wiſht to make all poſſible ſpéede from Babilon, for that wée were diſcouered there; ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus much further vnto vs, that there were letters from thence in all poſt addreſſed to ſtay vs.<note place="margin">A Carauan is a great many of Camels laden and men in a company, not much vnlike our Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iers (many in a company) heere in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> By chance this Carauan of Perſians were gone but one day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we receiued theſe Letters, and had they bin gone foure dayes before, wée would ſoone haue ouertaken them, in regard of their heauy lading. But after the receipt of theſe Letters, it was but like the ſpurring of the moſt frée horſe to haſten vs after them, for without taking leaue, we ſtole ſlily away, and were ſoone with them: who would not goe the direct way whither wée were bound, but paſſed through the <hi>Medes</hi> countrey, which was fiue or ſixe dayes iourney out of the way on pilgrimage, vnto a certaine Sanctorie, a prophet of theirs; whome we were mooued to accompany, more for feare, than for any deuotion. In which country, as wée paſſed, we ſaw (that which was ruth to ſée) the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ruines of maruelous great townes, which had (as it ſhould ſéeme) flouriſhed when the <hi>Medes</hi> triumphed, and their commonwealth proſpered. This pilgrimage ended, we went on from thence directly the courſe wée had determined: demanding of the Perſians, whether we had any more of the Turkiſh Gouernours to paſſe, who anſwered, they had one (&amp; that very mighty) called <hi>Cobat-bag,</hi> by whome we muſt of neceſſity paſſe. At which anſwer it had bin an eaſie matter to haue found a company of poore hearts néere their maiſters mouthes; for to vs remained no hope, but that we ſhuld haue bin
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177255:12"/>inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ted there. Yet, as God, and good for tune would, ſom of them (better bethinking themſelues) remembred another way, through one <hi>Heyder-bags</hi> country; who was neighbor to the other, howbeit at continual wars with him, in regard wherof we had good hope he would ayde vs. So entring the firſt night into this <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-bags</hi> countrey or iuriſdiction, the other hearing thereof; ſent vnto our company, that if we would not returne and come by him, hée woulde in the morning with his troupes cutte vs into gobbets. Then were wée in woorſe plight than at any time before: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding wée reſoluing to ſel our blouds as déere as wée coulde (ſince auoyde that extreamitie wée coulde not) wée there vppon ſooke heart of grace, and about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night wée aroſe with bag and baggage, and ſo held on our courſe through <hi>Heyder-bags</hi> country. When in the breake of the day wée might deſcry a troupe of horſes comming towardes vs, which wée verily imagined to be the ennemy: but wée were luckily deceiued, for it was he that gouerned that Countrey, who came to our ſuccours, and ſafely to conuoy vs through the ſame, hauing hadde ſome intelligence before of our progreſſe that way.</p>
            <p>Which hauing paſſed in ſafetie, through his gentle aſſiſtance and conduction, wée were indifferent well at hearts eaſe; albeit we had ſixe dayes iourney to paſſe (ere we ſhould enter the confines of <hi>Perſia</hi>) through the <hi>Courdes</hi> country, which is by interpretation the ſhéeus country. The people whereof are altogether addicted to théeuing, not much vnlike the wilde Iriſh, ſo that as we paſſed through them, euery night wée didde encampe, they ſlily ſtale more or leſſe from vs, watcht we neuer ſo warily: elſe woulde they doe but little hurte. This people doe liue altogether in Tents, kéeping of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177255:13"/> Hauing paſſed this pilfering people, we then happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entred the king of
<hi>Perſiaes</hi> country, where vpon our firſt entrance we thought we had bin imparadized, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our entertainement to be ſo good, and the maner of the people to be ſo kinde and curteous (farre differing from the Turkes) eſpecially when they heard we came of purpoſe to their king. We paſſed from the bordures nine daies iourney, ere wée came to
<hi>Casbin,</hi> where wée expected the reſidence of the king: during all which time we paſſed by no great Townes woorth the noting, vntil we came thither, hauing ſent a Currier before, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie what wée were, to the Gouernor of the Citty, leſt, by our ſodayne approch, our welcome ſhould haue bin the leſſe, and his maruell the more. Who therevpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs, a houſe of the kings, furniſht with ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments as befitted a great State. We came into the cittie by night, for that we would not be firſt ſéene in our trauelling apparrell. Howbeit the Gouernour the next morning, together with the chiefe of the kings houſe, came with a great traine, to ſalute ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him that his comming would be right pleaſing and acceptable to the king: but ſignified vnto him, that hée then was, in perſon, againſt the Tartares, his bordu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, with whome hée had warres) to whome, at that time, he had, in a pitched field, giuen a mightie ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe. And therevpon diſmiſt a poſte to the king, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying vnto him, that there was come, a chriſtian (right well attended) to ſée him, by reaſon of the great fame he had heard of him. Which when by the poſte he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, hée made as much expedition as poſſibly hée could (with reſpect had to his great affaires) to come to ſir
<hi>Anthony.</hi> There we remained ſome thrée wéeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came.</p>
            <p>In which time we were banquetted, and right roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally intreated, by the Gouernour and the kings Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177255:13"/>who brought vs to the kings gate, to offer that homage that all ſtrangers doe, that is, to kiſſe the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of his Pallace thrée times. Againſt the kings comming, wée apparrelled our ſelues in the beſt maner we could, with ſuch ſtuffe as we brought with vs, that is to ſay, ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> himſelfe in cloth of golde, the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per coate and vnder. His brother, in cloth of ſiluer, the vpper and vnder. Sixe Gentlemen, their lower coates ſilke, the vpper, cloth of ſiluer. Foure of his chiefeſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, in ſilke vnder-coates, the vpper, crimſin veluet. The reſt of his ſeruants, in a prettie kinde of bombaſte ſtuffe, all the vpper coats, watchet damaſke; our whole number being ſix and twenty, which made a very ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, the faſhion of our apparrell ſomwhat differing from the Perſian.</p>
            <p>Now by this time that we were thorowly thus fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and fitted, the king approched within fiue miles where he incamped: from whence he ſent to his Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, commaunding him to furniſh our company the next day with horſes, to the end we might come foorth to méete him on the way, which was performed an ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part accordingly. He comming in great triumph, hauing borne before him, aduaunced vpon pikes, one thouſand and two hundred heads of the conquered
<hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tares;</hi> whoſe king, and his ſonne, hée led along in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, hauing taken them priſoners: which triumph was continually more and more graced and augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by the country as hée paſſed, each one indeuouring (according to his power) to giue him welcome from the warres. Himſelfe being accompanied with all his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and great men in diuerſe troupes, that wee could not ſée any thing all the way, but men and horſes, with ſuch thundering of trumpets, kettle drummes (carried vpon camells) and ſuch like inſtruments of warre, that a man woulde haue thought, heauen and earth were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177255:14"/>tilting together. Their trumpets being all ſtraight, ſom two yards and an halfe in length, hauing ſuch a déepe, harſh, and horrible voyce, that it would amaze a man to heare them, if he neuer heard them before. At length we were brought into the preſence of the King, as hée thus paſſed in triumph: wee all diſmounting our horſes to kiſſe his foote (as the maner is) ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> firſt, who offering to performe that complement, the king, out of ſpeciall and vnuſuall fauour, put his hand betweene his mouth and his foote, and would not permit him to doe it, ſo all the reſt in order kiſſed his foote: which béeing done, the king called ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> vnto him, tolde him that hee was right heartily welcome to him, and to his country, which ere his departure he ſaide he ſhould find indéede. Who ſuffering not ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> to reply, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his horſe to be brought, and ſo we rode on next to the king. Where, in a while after, we might ſée a great troupe of curtezans of the citie come riding richly appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, to ſalute the king, and to welcome him from his warres. Their apparel little differing in faſhion from the mens, but only in their head attire and vpper coats. They weare bréeches, and ride aſtride as men do, and came with ſuch a crie as the wilde Iriſh make. The multitude of people were ſo great (conſiſting of Actors and Spectators) that we has much adoe in ſixe houres to paſſe thrée miles, which was from the place where we met the king, to the market place of the Cittie. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which at length being come, the king brought vs to the doore of the houſe where we ſhould alight, ſcituate in the ſame, commaunding one of his great men to place vs therein, whilſt himſelfe rid about ſome houre or two to ſée the ſhewes and matters of triumph perfourmed. Which being done, he returned to ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> where being ſet vpon the ground, with carpets vnder him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtome of the countrey, commaunding
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177255:14"/>ſtooles to be brought for ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> and his brother: there ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> made his Oration: which being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, the king diſcourſed with him of his trauelles, of his natiue countrey, the manner of gouernement there, and of diuerſe other things that accidentally became then ſubiect to their diſcourſe: the particularities whereof ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> anſwered, to the kings high contentment: and further, poſſeſt the king with ſuch a burning deſire to inuade the Turks dominions (by reaſon his ſtrength was ſo ſmall, as before is mentioned, and then at large ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> vnfolded) that he would on the very necke of that his late victorie, before his blood was colde (as it were) haue entred into action againſt the Turke, to the which ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> ceaſed not to animate him, for a double grudge hée bare him, to witte, for being ſuch a mortall ennemy to Chriſt, and for vſing them ſo like mortall ennemies, being chriſtians: howbeit, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition was, for a time, deferred, yet neuertheleſſe fully reſolued on. Theſe, and the like, made the King inſtantly to conceiue ſo excéeding well, and grew more and more into ſuch liking of ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> that once a day at the leaſt, he would ſend for him to conferre, and complement with him: yea ſometimes hée muſt be ſent for to come to his bed-chamber at midnight (accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with his brother) for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The king continued in that towne about ſome thirty dayes, where many nights the people entertained him with ſpectacles and ſhewes in their Baſars, which we doe call ſhoppes, all couered ouer head, as the Royall Exchange. At which alwayes we muſt méete the king. Their manner is to make the greateſt ſhew of thoſe wares they haue, in foure long ſtréetes, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt whereof is a round kinde of ſtage, couered with coſtly carpets, whereon is layde all kinde of fruites, confections, and wine for the king to banquet withall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:177255:15"/> After that he hath ſéene all the ſhewes, towardes night, they ſet vp as many lights as poſſible can ſtand one by another, conſiſting all of lamps; ſo that, by eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, there burneth at once in thoſe foure ſtréetes a hundred thouſand lamps, ſo cloſe vpon, and round about their ſtalls vpon the ground, that a man can hardly put his hand betwéene each lampe. After which ſights, he goeth to that place appointed for the banquet, where banqueting till midnight, béeing ſolaced all the while with all kinds of muſicke, of Inſtruments, and voice, with boyes and Curtezans, dauncing ſtrange kinds of Iigges and Lauoltaes: without which Curtezans, no banquet, be it neuer ſo coſtly hath any relliſh with them. Howbeit no mans wife comes thereat; neither is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (or if it be, very rarely) for a man once to ſée a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man if ſhée be once married, and her huſband liuing, no, though it be her owne naturall brother. So iclous are huſbands of their wiues loues and chaſtities, and ſuch cauſe of ſuſpition is there amongſt them in that reſpect. There is a cuſtome in that country, that if the King pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make any man great, by enoblizing him, he hath a very rich chaire ſette with ſtones carried after him, wherein he placeth that man at his banquet in publike aſſembly. This chaire was brought for ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> to ſit in, and he by the King placed therein accordingly. Which made the people much to admire that accident, in that hee vouchſafed that high fauour to a ſtranger, without deſert, or experience of his wórth: whereas ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomably he would haue great proofe of a mans wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, before he would ſo vouchſafe to dignifie him. Inſtantly as he cauſed ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> to ſit, he gaue him his owne girdle from about him for a further fauour: which was all of ſome golden ſtuffe, very curious and coſtly, thrée yards long, and an ell broade.</p>
            <p>Thrée dayes after he ſent a Preſent to ſir <hi>Anthony</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:177255:15"/>béeing a certaine demonſtration of the great eſtimation he hadde him in. Which was, fortie horſes furniſhed with ſaddles &amp;c. foure of which were very rich and faire, fit for the proper vſe of any Prince, twelue camels for carriage, together with fix mules, foure and twenty car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, moſt of them rich and faire, thrée Tents or Pauili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with all other neceſſaries of houſe; laſt of al, ſix men laden with ſiluer. The ſteward that brought it, tolde ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> that the King had ſent him that, to defray his charges till the next remoue, which was ten dayes off. I néede not ſpeake more of the Kings bountie, let the world, by this, imagin the reſt, and how he entreated Sir
<hi>Anthony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit the faſhion and mauer of the Perſians is not vnknowne to many of our Engliſh nation, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, by their owne trauells, attained that knowledge: or by reading, or credible report bin informed thereof: Yet ſomewhat to ſpeake touching the ſame, I hold it not altogether amiſſe, for the better information of thoſe (my countrymen) that doe not ſo well know it. For their ſitting at meate on the ground, with their manner of foode and féeding, it is much after the Turkiſh guiſe. Their deuotion as the Turkes, but ſomwhat different in religion. As the Perſian praieth only to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and <hi>Mortus Ally,</hi> the Turke to thoſe two, and to three other that were <hi>Mahomets</hi> ſeruants. Againſt which three, the Perſian ſtil inueighs, and hath in al townes, men that carry axes on their ſhoulders, challenging them to riſe againe, and they are there preſt to incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them by force of armes.</p>
            <p>They vſe much exerciſe, as hawking and hunting, with very much ſhooting. Their hawkes are excellent good, which they beare on their right hand, without hood or bell.</p>
            <p>The merchandize and commodities which <hi>Perſia</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177255:16"/>yéeldeth, are ſilkes, both rawe, and otherwiſe, of all ſutes and colours. Spices, drugges, pearles, and other pretious Iems: together with carpets of diuers kinds. Theſe, with many other commodities of this nature, <hi>Perſia</hi> plentifully affoordeth.</p>
            <p>They write from the right ſide of the paper to the left like the Turkes, contrary to our manner. Their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Characters being ſo irregular, and (as we would thinke) deformed, that to vs it ſéemeth the writing of ſome vtterly vnſkilfull in letters or learning, or as a wilde kind of ſcribling, that hath therein neither forme nor matter: howbeit they affirm their writing is moſt compendious, and euery letter (well néere) with his circumfler importeth a whole word, though conſiſting of many ſillables.</p>
            <p>They haue not many Bookes, much leſſe great Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braries amongſt their beſt Clarkes. They are no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nation, but ignorant in all kinde of liberall or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sciences, and almoſt of all other Arts and Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, except it be in certaine things pertaining to hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes furniture, and ſome kindes of carpettings and ſilke workes, wherein they excell.</p>
            <p>They haue neither golde nor ſiluer from any mines of their owne, for they haue none: howbeit they haue money made of both kindes, in great plenty, together with ſome ſmall coyne made of copper, like our <hi>Briſtow</hi> tokens.</p>
            <p>Theyr conceit of Chriſt is, that hée was a very great Prophet, and a moſt holy and religious man, but no way comparable to <hi>Mahomet:</hi> for <hi>Mahomet</hi> (ſay they) was that finall prophet, by whom all things were, and are to be perfected and conſummated. They further ſay, that becauſe God had neuer wife, therefore Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be his ſonne.</p>
            <p>If any man conſpire treaſon againſt the king, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177255:16"/>capitally offend him, hée is puniſhed, not onely in his owne perſon, but in his whole Tribe.</p>
            <p>If they affirme any matter with an othe, they ſwear by God and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or <hi>Mortus Ally:</hi> and when they would be beléeued, they ſweare by all thrée at once.</p>
            <p>They circumciſe their children at ſeauen yéeres olde, according to the cuſtome of their neighbour the Turks.</p>
            <p>In making water, the men kowre downe like the women, and when they doe it, they haue a ſpowte or ſpringer, to ſpirt ſome parte of their water vppon their priuy partes, aſwell men as women, which they holde as a kinde of religious duty, and which in no ſort muſt be neglected.</p>
            <p>They buy and ſell men and women in the market, which is a principal merchandiſe of theirs among them ſelues. If they buy any yoong women there, they féele them euery where. If a man buy a bond-woman for his owne carnalitie, and ſhe prooue falſe to him, hée may (by their lawe) kill her, as he may a dog in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>In praying, they turne their faces towardes the South, as wee doe towardes the Eaſt, becauſe
<hi>Mecha</hi> where <hi>Mahomet</hi> is encoffined in yron (which by force of a Temples roofe, conſiſting of Adamant, hangeth, as it were, by way of myracle in the ayre) lieth in
<hi>Arabia,</hi> which is South from them. To which, whoſoeuer ſhall go on pilgrimage (as many of them doe) they are euer held for moſt holy and ſacred Saintes, which they call
<hi>Setes,</hi> and not onely themſelues are ſo reputed, but the poſteritie of that man are ſo accounted, and of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are ſo perſwaded. For if one ſhall in any thing contradict them, either in ſaying or in dooing, they will ouer-rule him, and exact credit and beléefe with all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, by ſaying he is a Saint at leaſt, and therefore, on paine of damnation, muſt be beléeued, and highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéemed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177255:17"/>although hée lie neuer ſo loudely, and do neuer ſo lewdly.</p>
            <p>Their buildings are (for the moſt parte) made of bricke, hardned in the ſand, not made with fire, as durs are: wherein they haue very little furniture other then carpets vpon their floores; and ſuch the pooreſt man hath, but the goodnes thereof is according to the abilitie of the owners: their houſes are all made with flatte roofes without, couered with a kinde of plaiſter, or earth ſpred plaiſterwiſe.</p>
            <p>Néere vnto a towne called <hi>Backo</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> there iſſueth out of the earth in the manner of a water-ſpring, a certaine kind of oyle, in great abundance, which they (from all parts of the Perſian dominions) do fetch vpon Camels, Kine, and Aſſes, to burne in lamps, which are the lights they vſe in their houſes.</p>
            <p>The people are now very curteous, vſing all ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with great kindneſſe and ciuilitie, eſpecially ſince this King hath gouerned. Howbeit (by report) they haue béene heretofore little better (in that reſpect) then the Turks.</p>
            <p>The names of the parts of <hi>Perſia,</hi> that in times paſt were diſtinct kingdomes, are
<hi>Caſuin, Haſphane, Seraze, Knghgollo, Suſter, Curdiſtan, Hammadan, Kirman,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<hi>Corrozan.</hi> Theſe this King had when he came firſt to the crowne; theſe following he tooke and wan ſince. <hi>Tuntabas, Coffe, Corrazon, Buchora, Vrgans, Taskane, Strabat,</hi> the kingdoms of <hi>Maſcendran, Marcu, Ruſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, Nure-cugge.</hi> The kingdomes of
<hi>Ieglands;</hi> the firſt <hi>Iegland, Reaſt, Saughtoſer, Caskeger, Tawlis, Aderbeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan,</hi> béeing a great kingdome.</p>
            <p>Theſe townes following were loſt by his Predeceſſors to the Turke. <hi>viz. Tawris, Seruan, Samachy, Iange, Berthe,</hi> with many others; which the Perſian doth now hope to recouer; béeing farre better able then in times
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177255:17"/>paſt, for that he hath drawne all the fore-mentioned townes and parts into his poſſeſſion: which, when his Predeceſſors would inuade the Turke before, theſe would impeach and molleſt them behinde: ſo that now he ſtands ſecure from all inuaſion of the borderers, whereby he is able to carry all his force cléere, without interruption againſt the Turke, which at the leaſt will be foure hundred thouſand ſtrong. Vpon which vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking he is (as before was mentioned) fully reſolued: but firſt by ſir
<hi>Anthonies</hi> aduice, he is determined to ioyne in league, amitie, and confederacie with the Chriſtian princes, by meanes whereof, he may the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preuaile in his purpoſe, and thereby vtterly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Turke. Howbeit his councellers were all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately bent againſt theſe determinations and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedings at the firſt, yet the king with his generall, who is a <hi>Georgian</hi> Chriſtian (ſtill animated and prouoked therevnto by ſir
<hi>Anthonies</hi> forcible perſwaſions) were reſolute and confident in the cauſe, and béeing ſo irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouable, at laſt preuailed, and all the reſt abſolutely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. And by that mutuall conſent of the king and his counſell, no man was thought ſo ſit to be imployed in Embaſſie to the chriſtian princes (to the purpoſe aboue recited) as ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> béeing a Chriſtian, and the firſt mouer of the king to theſe vndertakings, appointing a great man of the Perſians to accompany him in thoſe buſineſſes, but the whole burden thereof to lie onely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> who vndertooke the ſame accordingly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Which béeing concluded, and thus vndertaken, wée were ready to departe from the Kings court, lying then at <hi>Haſphane,</hi> when ſuddainly there came newes of a Portingall fryer, that was comming thither, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with two other fryers, and foure ſeruants: this fryer ſtayed ſome thrée miles off the towne, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177255:18"/>ſent the other two with letters to ſir <hi>Anthony;</hi> whereby he ſignified vnto him that he was the laſt King of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingales brother, and that hee was ſent by the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> as Procurator generall of al the Eaſt Indies. Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> beléeuing it, went himſelfe, accompanied with as many chriſtians as he could get, to the Frigot. And after mutuall gréetings, hée tolde ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> that hearing of his great and weighty buſineſſes, and ſo godly a worke (he being a great biſhoppe of the king of <hi>Spaines</hi>) came poſting night and day to aſſiſt him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Which ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> was right glad of, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the ſame the better, hée brought him along to his owne houſe, and there diſlodged his brother to lodge him.</p>
            <p>This being doone, hée tolde ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> that hée greatly deſired to ſée the King, for that hée had a preſent to beſtow on him, which ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> ſoone procured. But now, by the way, this preſent was deliuered him in truſt, to be deliuered to the king, howbeit hée preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it in his owne name, in requitall whereof the King gaue him a Crucifixe woorth (by eſtimation) a hundred pounds and better: which villany, and many others, ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> afterwards diſcouered, though the meane while he held him for a holy man.</p>
            <p>Ere we departed from the King, he would faine (by the Kings Commiſſion) haue bin an Agent in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent action, wherein ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> was principally em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, and likely he was to haue bin one, with vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall conſent, but that the writings &amp; all other things therevnto incident were before perfected and finiſhed. And ſéeing he could be no actor (as hée defired) by reaſon thereof, hee intreated ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> to procure the Kings fauourable letters, in his behalfe, to the Pope, and the King of <hi>Spaine;</hi> which ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> did accordingly. In requitall whereof, he beganne (vnder-hand) to deale
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177255:18"/>with thoſe of the Kings councell, which had bin backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the beginning of theſe buſineſſes, who aſſured them, that ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> was not able to performe ſo great a negotiation. Which ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> perceiuing, hée made all the haſte he poſſibly could to be gone, the rather, becauſe hée had waded ſomewhat too farre with this execrable frier, who the firſt night he lodged in ſir <hi>Anthonies</hi> houſe, found the meanes to haue a Perſian curtezan to lie with him, and ſo had night by night du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his continuannce there; which if he wanted, hée would hyre a boy zodomitically to vſe. And that he was a zodomiticall wretch, it dooth appeare hereby: ſir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> at his firſt comming, bought twoo chriſtian boies in the market, which afterwardes he beſtowed on this Frier, whoſe name was <hi>Nicolao deMelo.</hi> He no ſooner had them, but hée was in hand with them concerning his zodomiticall villany. The boyes finding whereto hée was inclined (beeing inceſſauntly importuned by him, to yéelde to his beaſtly deſire, complained to him that ſolde them, hée likewiſe to the Officer, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to the King, by meanes whereof the King eſpied his villany. Whereuppon the king ſent for the boyes from him, and ſent him worde, that were it not for ſir <hi>Anthonies</hi> ſake, he ſhould looſe his head.</p>
            <p>Soone after wée departed, taking the Frier and one of his fellowes with vs, hauing eightéene dayes iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from the Perſian Court to <hi>Iegland,</hi> where wée were imbarked to croſſe the Caſpian ſea. In which time, the frier confeſſed hée was but an ordinary Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine frier, and in a gameſome vaine hée further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed how he woulde bring mennes wiues, after hée had ſhriuen them, to his bent, as taking aduantage of their confeſſed faultes: and to cloſe vppe this, and ſuch like good talke in the day, wée ſhoulde be ſure to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177255:19"/>take him with a whoore at night. And I will tell you a ieaſt concerning him, which I hadde almoſt forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>One day, at <hi>Casbin</hi> hée ſent his man to a whoore, fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her with two Chickins, (which is two rialles) to come vnto him at night, taking vppon him the name of the Embaſſador. The kinde wench being true of promiſe, came vnto ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> who demaunding the cauſe of her comming, ſhee tolde him all, &amp;c. So the wench went away
<hi>gratis</hi> with the money, the frier not daring to demaund it.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing merrily paſſed the time with this ſory Frier, and being come to the place where we ſhoulde be imbarked, wée ſtayed there one moneth for the Perſian Péere, that was to goe along with vs, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is mentioned.</p>
            <p>Vpon whoſe comming, wée preſently imbarked our ſelues for <hi>Haſter-caune,</hi> which is the firſt landing place of the Emperour of <hi>Ruſciaes</hi> countrey to
<hi>Perſia</hi> ward.</p>
            <p>Vpon the <hi>Caſpian</hi> ſea (which wée were to croſſe) wée were two moneths before wée landed: which time wée indured with much paine, and no leſſe feare, hauing (beſides the naturall roughneſſe of the ſea) very much foule and ſtormy weather: by reaſon whereof wée had béene like to haue ſuffered ſhippewracke, which twice ſtrooke on ground, ſo that wée were conſtrained to diſburden the ſame of a great parte of our ſubſtaunce. Howbeit in the end God ſo bleſſed vs, that in two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths wee came to our wiſhed harborow. Where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arriued, the Gouernor hauing intelligence of our landing, ſent a Captayne with a guarde to receiue vs, and to conduct vs to the caſtle of
<hi>Haſter-caune,</hi> where was landed but the day before, an Embaſſadour that the King of
<hi>Perſia</hi> had ſent a moneth before, onely to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177255:19"/>make our paſſage through the Emperour of <hi>Ruſcia</hi> his countrey.</p>
            <p>From which caſtle to <hi>Muſco</hi> towne we were, by ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and by land, tenne wéekes paſſing. All which time ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> and his company, with the other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, and their attendants, were all at the charge of the <hi>Ruſcian</hi> Emperour (for ſo is the cuſtome of that Country, to all Trauellers of that nature, as long as they are paſſing through his dominions) who eates ſuch meate as is brought before them
<hi>gratis,</hi> hauing withall, a guarde ſet ouer them, ſo that they are little better then priſoners, as long as they are within the limites of his territories.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Haſter-caune</hi> we paſit by bote along the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Riuer of <hi>Volgo,</hi> vntill we canie to a towne named <hi>Negſon,</hi> which was ſeauen weekes paſſage. In which time, wée ſawe nothing woorthy the noting, but thrée or foure woodden Eaſtles or Blocke-houſes to guarde that Riuer, which Riuer dooth bring maruellous great commodities to the Emperour, and to the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>Diuerſe <hi>Tartars</hi> paſſing from place to place about that Riuer, liuing in little houſes made vpon whéeles, and are carried too and fro, hauing aboundaunce of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, liue ſo in ſubiection to the Emperor, paying him tribute, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>One onely faire Cittie we ſaw all that while called <hi>Gaſſane,</hi> wherein wee were: from whence wée paſſed to <hi>Negſon</hi> a or ſayd, where, by the way, fel out a tarre betwéene ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> and the other Embaſſador, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> preſumed to reprehend him for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers miſdemeanors which hée committed, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of his king and countrey: Inſomuch, that had wée not had guarde in our company, one of vs had killed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177255:20"/>another. Leauing héere a while, I will turne agayne to the Frier, who was by this time growne into mortall hatred wyth hys fellow Frier, of whome before I ſpake, whoſe name was <hi>Alfonſo,</hi> a Frier of the order of Saint <hi>Francis.</hi> Which Frier had acquainted ſir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> that Frier <hi>Nicolao</hi> had ſpent his life moſt lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Indiaes,</hi> the particularities whereof hée at large related.</p>
            <p>Morcouer, hée tolde hym, that by reaſon of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious life, the king of
<hi>Spaine</hi> had ſent for hym, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hée did much more hurte than good in thoſe parts, but neuer would come vntill nowe that hée was going thitherward.</p>
            <p>He alſo tolde ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> that that preſent which hée deliuered the king of <hi>Perſia</hi> in his owne name, was ſent by a friend of the kings from <hi>Ormous,</hi> by another, who had withal, a letter to the king. Which bearer, (béeing of his acquaintance) hée inueigled and inticed, by the gift of fifty Crownes, and ſayre wordes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer hym the preſent, together with the Letter to carry to the king, who finally preuayled wyth hym. And when hée came to <hi>Perſia,</hi> hée ſuppreſſed the letter, but delyuered the preſent in his owne name, as béefore is declared.</p>
            <p>Vppon diſcouery of which villanies, ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> tooke hym priſoner, and earried him along wyth hym, as one depriued of former liberty.</p>
            <p>And being come to <hi>Negſon,</hi> we ſtayed there neare hand a moneth. Towardes the end whereof the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſent a great man of his Court thither, for to accompany and conduct vs to
<hi>Muſco,</hi> who gaue the preheminence to the Perſian Embaſſador, in that hée was Embaſſadour to the Emperour from the Perſian, and ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> but a paſſenger through his countrey,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177255:20"/>as hée eſtéemed hym, and ſo did vſe at his pleaſure, to fir <hi>Anthonies</hi> ſmall contentment, vntill we came to <hi>Muſco,</hi> where wée were entertayned in the beſt forte they could, wyth a crue of <hi>aqua vitae</hi>-bellyed fellowes, clad in coates of cloth of gold: which ſhew being ended, for the firſt encounter thoſe coates were put vp agayne into the Treaſury or Wardrobe, and wée ſhut vp in priſon for tenne dayes, yea all acceſſe of others to vs, or we to them was thereby vtterly harred. In which time wée ſent to entreate, that eyther our Engliſh merchants might be permitted to come toovs, or that wée might goe or ſend to them for neceſſaries, becauſe we were not fitted wyth clothes, (as we thought) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for the Emperors preſence.</p>
            <p>Where vpon the Lord Chauncellor ſent for the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, enquyring of them what ſir
<hi>Anthony</hi> was, and whether they durſt giue hym any credite. To whome they replyed, that hée was nobly deſcended, and alied euen to the beſt men of <hi>England:</hi> yea, and that they woulde giue hym credite for as much as they were woorth.</p>
            <p>Here vppon they had liberty to ſend vs ſuch neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as wée ſent for, but no liberty to come to vs, much leſſe we to them.</p>
            <p>The tenth day wée were ſent for to come before the Emperor after theyr order, which was, to lay downe in a note, howe euery man ſhoulde bee marſhalled in comming (béeing all on horſebacke) wherein the Perſian Embaſſadour was appoynted by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to haue the firſt and chiefe place, the next, that Perſian that was ſent but to accompany ſir
<hi>Anthony,</hi> and the laſt of the thrée ſhoulde be ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſefie.</p>
            <p>Which when ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> perceyued, hée vtterly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177255:21"/>refuſed to goe in that order, becauſe that he, to whoſe truſt and charge the whole buſineſſe had béene cemmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by whome the ſame was ſolely procured: by which <hi>Perſia</hi> likewiſe ſhoulde be infinitely benefited (ſpecially he being a chriſtian, and they Pagans) ſhould be put hindermoſt in the march, that was the formoſt in the matter.</p>
            <p>By the meanes of which refuſall, hée purchaſed the Emperours diſpleaſure: and to manifeſt the ſame, firſt hée tooke the Frier from ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> and gaue him his libertie to goe whither hée thought good. Next, hée daily ſent his great Dukes to examine ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diuers friuolous particularities, to prooue, if they thereby might groape out ſome matter of aduantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
            <p>Thus daily hée was extreamely vexed and moleſted by the Emperour, the Perſian Embaſſadour, withall, ſetting on the Frier vnder-hand, to deuiſe all the villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hée could againſt him, as to ſay, hée knew ſir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> to be but a man of meane parentage, and alſo, that hee was come but as a Spic through the Countrey for purpoſes tending to his owne good, and not of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> and Chriſtendome, as hée pretended. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they tooke all the kings Letters from him, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, to know the purport thereof.</p>
            <p>Soone after ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> and the Frier were brought before the Commiſſioners to be further examined: where ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> (béeing inflamed with choler, by reaſon of his excéeding ill vſage, notwithſtanding the goodneſſe of the cauſe of his comming) demaunded whether the Emperour did euer purpoſe to ſend any Embaſſadours to any other Countries? Proteſting, that if euer hée mette with them in any partes of the world, beſides theyr owne, hée would indeuour to let
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177255:21"/>them knowe hée was not halfe ſo well intreated in <hi>Ruſcia,</hi> as the cauſe of his comming of right deſerued, and the Emperour, by the lawes diuine and ciuil ought to haue perfourmed, and the rather, becauſe hée was a Chriſtian, ſuch as hée pretends himſelfe to be, and came (as became a chriſtian) for the generall good of al Chriſtendome, the Perſian being ſtirred vp therevnto by his onely meanes. Wherevpon the Frier in terms thwarted ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> whoſe blood already boyled, with the exceſſe of his chollers heate, which as then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded. And being by that graceleſſe and vngratefull Frier further prouoked, hee (not able, though inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſhould haue died for it) to ſuppreſſe his heate, gaue the fatte Frier ſuch a ſound box on the face (his double cauſe of choller redoubling his might, deſire of reuenge withall augmenting the ſame) that downe falles the Frier, as if hée had béene ſtrooke with a thunder-bolt. Which béeing doone, (with that courage and high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution which well appéered in his lookes, wordes, and déedes) they foorthwith gaue ouer examination, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had too far examined ſir <hi>Anthonies</hi> patience, which well they with feare (as I thinke) ſawe, and the Frier (almoſt paſt feare) did farre better féele. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they went inſtantly to the Emperour, and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him of all that had happened, and howe ſir
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> was reſolued. For which (as by the euent it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péered) hée was vſed the better. For from thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward we had liberty to go to the Engliſhmen, of whom we were very honorably entertained, and royally fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Howbeit wée were conſtrained to remaine there ſixe moneths, expecting euery day (for all this) ſome miſchiefe to be doone vnto vs, or to be ſent into ſome parte of his country to be kept, where wée ſhoulde not haue heard from our friendes in haſte, which we feared
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177255:22"/>worſe then death. Yet, in the end, wée were eftſoones ſent for before the priuy councell, where ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> had his charge to be gone, which was no ſmall ioy to vs all.</p>
            <p>But the day before wée left <hi>Muſcouia,</hi> it was my fortune to ſée the King, and his Quéene, in cerimonious and triumphant manner paſſing out of the Citty, with a great Image, and a huge Bell, to offer to a certayne Friery ſome thirty miles off, which was performed in this ſorte. Firſt, all the morning diuers troupes of horſe paſſed out of the Citty, to ſtand ready to receiue him at his comming out of the gate. About midday the King ſetting forwards, his guard formoſt, all on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, to the number of fiue hundred, all clad in ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel coats, riding in ranke, thrée and three, with bows, and arrowes, and ſwords girt to them, as alſo hatchets vnder the one thigh. After the guarde were ledde, by twenty men, twenty goodly horſes, with very rich and curious ſaddles, and ten more for his ſonne and heire apparant, béeing a childe of twelue yeeres of age. After which was ledde, in like ſorte, twenty beutifull white horſes, for the Quéenes chariots, hauing onely vppon them a fine ſheete, and on theyr heades a crimeſin vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet bridle. After them came a great number of Friers in theyr rich coapes, ſinging, carrying many pictures and lights. After them followed the greateſt parte of the merchants of the Citty. Next them was ledde the Kings horſe, for that day, together with his ſonnes: the kings ſaddle and furniture moſt richly beſette with ſtones of great price and beauty. Then followed the Patriarch, wyth all the Archbiſhoppes, Biſhoppes, and great Prelates ſinging in their coapes, very rich and glorious, hauing huge Images borne before them, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very richly inlayed, with pretious Iems of diuerſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177255:22"/>colours, and lights about them. Then followed the king himſelfe, who had in his left hand his ſonne aboue mentioned, and in his right hand his cappe. Next him came the Quéene, ſupported on eyther ſide by two olde Ladies, hir face euen thickely plaiſtered with painting, as were the other Ladies (according to the cuſtome of the Countrey) hir body very groſſe, hir eyes hollowe and far into hir head, attended with ſome thrée ſcore very fayre women (if painting (which they holde a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter religious) deceiued not the iudgement of mine eie.) All whoſe apparel was very rich, beſet with pearle cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly wrought, hauing white hattes on theyr heads, wyth great round bands laden wyth pearle. We ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſawe hattes worne by any women in the Country, but by them onely. Next vnto them was drawne thrée huge chariots, the firſt with tenne fayre white horſes, two and two, the ſecond with eight, and the third with ſixe in like order: which chariots were al very rich and gorgeous within and without. After which, all the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men paſſed in coaches. Then was caried, in a great cheſt, the forenamed Image, guarded by a great man and State of the Country, with ſome fiue hundred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his commaund, for the guarde and conuoy of that Image. And laſt of all came that huge bell, béeing of twenty tunne weight, drawne by thrée thouſand and fiue hundred men (not being poſſible to be drawne by oxen or horſes) in manner following. They faſtned ſixe excéeding long hawſers, or mighty great gable ropes in ſix lengths to the frame whereon the bell was placed. In this ranke of ropes were placed thoſe thrée thouſand and ſixe hundred men, with litle cordes ouer their ſhoulders, faſtned to the great hawſers, drawing after the manner of our Weſterne barge-men héere in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:177255:23"/> The poyſe of the Bell was ſo g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at, that paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the ſtréetes of <hi>Muſco</hi> (being paued wyth great ſquare péeces of timber ſette cloſe one by another) the woodde of the frame or carriage whereon the bell was drawne, ſet the timber of the ſtréets on fire, through both the woods chaſing togither, ſo that ſome were faine to followe hard after, to throwe on water, as the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers beganne to ſmoake. And thus was this bell and the Image eonueyed to the Friery, as hath afore béene ſayde.</p>
            <p>The next day following we tooke our iourney (that is to ſay, in mid Maie) towards Saint
<hi>Nicolas</hi> to take ſhipping, which was ſome ſixe wéekes paſſage by land and riuer. During all which time, we ſaw nothing, in a maner, but woods and water. But being come to the ſea ſide, being the place where wée were to take ſhip, we ſtayed there one moneth for prouiſion for our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>In which time we were diuers times inuited aboorde Engliſh ſhippes, where we were roially banquetted at the Agents charges and the merchants. To the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization of which banquets we had thrée hundred hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred great ſhot. And as we ſtayed there, one Maiſter
<hi>Megricke</hi> a merchant came from <hi>Muſco,</hi> and brought the Friers two letters wyth hym, reporting that the Lord Chauncallor, in ſatiſfaction of the wrong and ill vſage he extended to ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> ſent after the Frier to the borders, who tooke both his letters and all his ſubſtance that he had deceitfully and lewdly gotten in many yeares before in the <hi>Indiaes</hi> from him, leauing him not ſo much as his Friers wéede: and whether hée cauſed his throate to be cut, it was vncertayne, but not vnlike.</p>
            <p>Thus, as this lewd wretch had (as peraduenture he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177255:23"/>thought) paſſed the pikes of Gods iudgements bent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and threatening his ruine, for his ſeuerall villanies, and that (as to him perhappes it ſéemed) hée was nowe euen entring the confines of his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, furniſhed with Letters in his commendation, from the Perſian mighty Potentate, to his liege lord the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> whereby hée thought to haue attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (notwithſtanding his former leud life in the <hi>Indies</hi>) great reputation and preferment, euen then was hée ouertaken wyth a vengeance, and payed home with a miſchiefe, to the vtter loſſe of his Letters, wherein ſo much hée ioyed, his ſubſtance that was all his liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loode, and (as it is moſt likely) of his life, the leudneſſe whereof brought vppon him theſe vnexpected (yet well deſerued) miſeries.</p>
            <p>A good caueat for all thoſe, that vnder God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties coate, will play all diuelliſh prankes, whereof there are but too many (in theſe laſt dayes, and therefore the worſt dayes) crept into his holy church, in all quarters of Chriſtendome, making the ſame ſacred houſe of pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (which ought with all prayer and holy indeuor to bée preſerued from all pollution and polluted perſons) a very denne of théeues, as it is in the Goſpel, that walke continually in ſhéepes clothing, but inwardely they are rauening Woolues: They are knowne by theyr workes.</p>
            <p>From hence wée tooke ſhippe for <hi>Stoade,</hi> béeing ſixe wéekes vppon the Sea, ere wée coulde recouer it. In which time we were continually toſſed and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with contrary Windes: and once had béene like to haue béene vtterly caſt away, ſo that wée all were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelmed in deſpayre, as wée were at poynt to be in the Sea, but that (by Gods protection and direction) we (paſt all expectation) fell vppon the Flie. Where,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177255:24"/>(hauing diuers Letters of ſir <hi>Anthonies</hi> to his friendes in
<hi>England</hi>) I parted from hin (he holding his courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Emperor of
<hi>Germany:</hi>) from thence I came to the <hi>Taſſel</hi> then to the <hi>Firme:</hi> ſo to the <hi>Hage:</hi> from the <hi>Hage</hi> to <hi>Vluſhing:</hi> And finally, from thence to
<hi>Douer,</hi> where I landed in the middeſt of the moneth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, in the thrée and fortieth yéere of the Quéenes Maieſties raigne, and in the yéere of our Lorde God, one thouſand ſixe hundred and one.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:177255:24"/>
            <head>I. D. <hi>of</hi> Hereford <hi>in praiſe of</hi> William Parry Gentleman.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TO creepe like <hi>Ants</hi> about this earthie <hi>Round,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And not to gather with the <hi>Ant,</hi> is vaine:</l>
               <l>Some finde out <hi>Countries</hi> which were neuer found,</l>
               <l>Yet ſcarcely get their labour for their paine:</l>
               <l>Whereby I gather, there they gather not,</l>
               <l>But rather ſcatter. Better loſt than found</l>
               <l>Were all ſuch <hi>Countries. Will,</hi> ſuch is thy lot,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt loſt ground, to finde out other ground,</l>
               <l>Yet thou haſt found much more than thou couldſt loſe,</l>
               <l>Thogh thou couldſt loſe more than the Seas confine,</l>
               <l>For thou haſt found that, none could finde, but thoſe</l>
               <l>That ſeeke, as thou haſt done, for <hi>Wiſedomes</hi> eine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>And that's Experience, no where to be ſeene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But eu'ry where, where thou</hi> (<hi>good</hi> Will) <hi>hast beene.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Tam Arte Quam Marie.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
